Speaker 1: In case you're wondering, I'm shooting from sunny but deeply unwell California for the Pacific
Speaker 1: Bitcoin conference. Meanwhile, back in the real world, yet another Federal Reserve official is
Speaker 1: warning that more rate hikes are coming in the wake of inflation that's been re-accelerating for
Speaker 1: two months straight, with more to come going by the warnings. Speaking at a conference in Alberta,
Speaker 1: which is the least crazy part of Canada, Fed board member Michelle Bauman warned, quote,
Speaker 1: inflation continues to be too high, so she expects more rate hikes to, quote, return inflation to our
Speaker 1: 2% goal in a timely way. Note how transitory has now been demoted to timely, perhaps again with more
Speaker 1: to come. Other Fed officials have made similar recent warnings, including Cleveland Fed President
Speaker 1: Loretta Mester and John Williams of the New York Fed. The background here is that inflation has been
Speaker 1: stuck for two and a half years, core inflation anyway, which is the one the Fed cares about. They
Speaker 1: see that as real inflation. But that has now shifted to headline inflation speeding up again.
Speaker 1: That's the one that you see in the newspaper, and that is the one they most fear because it gets voters
Speaker 1: riled up. Now that is not supposed to be happening with the highest interest rates in 22 years,
Speaker 1: and the fastest interest rate hikes in roughly 50 years. So why is inflation going up again?
Speaker 1: Because in those two and a half years, the Fed has made zero progress on the actual driver of
Speaker 1: inflation, which is out of control federal spending. In fact, it's gotten a lot worse,
Speaker 1: with the Congressional Budget Office now projecting two trillion deficits through 2050. Instead, central
Speaker 1: banks have been coasting on freebies as supply chains unstuck and looming global recession hit energy
Speaker 1: prices. Now that the energy is taking back the freebie, as Warren Buffett likes to put it,
Speaker 2: the tide went out, and we see who is swimming without a suit. So backing up, inflation jumped
Speaker 2: in 2021 because of obscene levels of federal spending to buy lockdowns. At one point, almost one in three
Speaker 1: dollars had fresh ink on it. Then lockdowns eased, the world digested Mr. Putin's war, and prices started
Speaker 1: coming back down. But the central bankers had already hiked rates. So far, so fast, the global recession was
Speaker 1: now incoming. That hit energy prices hard, which are a big part of CPI. That's the progress they've been
Speaker 1: making. In the 2008 crisis, for example, oil went from 196 dollars to 61 in just six months. In the 2020
Speaker 1: lockdowns, oil hit 22 bucks. For a minute, it actually had a negative price. So that cheap oil, alas, turned out to be very
Speaker 1: transitory since Joe Biden and his European comrades are now wiping out domestic energy production in
Speaker 1: favor of unicorn farts. And so energy supply is evaporating. Moreover, this gives OPEC an opening
Speaker 1: to cut their own production since they don't have to worry about American shale producers drinking their
Speaker 1: milkshakes. So at this point, the energy freebie is going away. It's even reversing because of the West's
Speaker 1: suicidal energy policies, leaving the government spending, which was never fixed. So what's next?
Speaker 1: Brought to you by Unchained. What's next is more hikes to crush the real economy so central bankers can
Speaker 1: avoid those uncomfortable conversations about government deficits or the net zero utopia that
Speaker 1: aims to return us to the medieval era. I mentioned recently that we're seeing warnings that bonds could
Speaker 1: go a lot higher, driven by ongoing inflation and eye-watering deficits. Those together make investors
Speaker 1: wonder if Uncle Sam actually intends to pay its debts. Given $33 trillion in debt, any jump in bonds
Speaker 2: could be the spark that takes us over the edge. Okay, we'll be watching. See you next time.